Being a child, and sort of crawling around the house,
في طفولتي اعتدت اللعب حول المنزل،
I remember these Turkish carpets,
ولازلت اتذكر تلك السجادة التركية،
and there were these scenes, these battle scenes, these love scenes.
كان عليها بعض رسومات المعارك , رسومات جميلة حقاً.
I mean, look, this animal is trying to fight back this spear
انظر الى الحيوان الذي يحاول ان يتفادى الرمح
from this soldier.
من هذا الفارس.
And my mom took these pictures actually, last week,
في الحقيقة , امي قامت بالتقاط هذة الصورة في الأسبوع الماضي،
of our carpets, and I remember this to this day.
من تلك السجادة التي لازلت اتذكرها جيداً.
There was another object, this sort of towering piece of furniture
كان هناك ايضاً قطعة اثاث على شكل حصن
with creatures and gargoyles and nudity --
عليها بعض المنحوتات, والتماثيل, والمجسمات --
pretty scary stuff, when you're a little kid.
اشياء تخيف فعلاً, اذا ما كنت صبياً صغيراً.
What I remember today from this is that objects tell stories,
ما اتذكره اليوم من هذ الاشياء, ان تلك المجسمات تحكي قصة،
so storytelling has been a really strong influence in my work.
لذلك رواية القصص كانت عامل قوي يؤثر على عملي.
And then there was another influence.
بالاضافة الى عامل مؤثر اخر.
I was a teenager, and at 15 or 16, I guess like all teenagers,
حين كنت في عمر الخامسة عشر, مثل كل المراهقين،
we want to just do what we love and what we believe in.
كنا نقوم بفعل الاشياء التي نحبها , ونؤمن بها.
And so,
بالتالي،
I fused together the two things I loved the most,
قمت بجمع الشيئين الذين احبهما،
which was skiing and windsurfing.
وهما التزلج والطائرة الشراعية.
Those are pretty good escapes from the drab weather in Switzerland.
وكانت تلك حيلة جيدة للهروب من البيئة المملة في سويسرا.
So, I created this compilation of the two:
فقمت بصنع هذة الاختراع:
I took my skis and I took a board and I put a mast foot in there,
فجمعت المزلجتان مع لوح , وصنعت مكان للاقدام،
and some foot straps, and some metal fins,
وبعض اربطة الجزم و والاجزاء المعدنية،
and here I was, going really fast on frozen lakes.
وكنت اتزلج بها بسرعه على بحيرة جليدية.
It was really a death trap. I mean, it was incredible,
في الحقيقة, كانت شديدة الخطورة , لكنها مذهلة فعلاً،
it worked incredibly well, but it was really dangerous.
كانت مذهلة جداً, لكنها أيضاً خطيرة في نفس الوقت.
And I realized then I had to go to design school.
بعدها . ادركت بان علي الالتحاق بمدرسة للتصاميم الفنية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, look at those graphics there.
ويمكنكم النظر إلى هذة الرسوم هنا.
So, I went to design school,
فالتحقت فعلا بمدرسة للتصاميم الفنية،
and it was the early '90s when I finished.
تخرجت في بداية التسعينات،
And I saw something extraordinary happening in Silicon Valley,
وكان هناك شي مثير جدا يحدث في وادي السيلكون،
so I wanted to be there,
فتمنيت ان اكون هناك،
and I saw that the computer was coming into our homes,
حين لاحظت ان الكبيوتر اصبح ياخذ مكاناً مهما في حياتنا.
that it had to change in order to be with us in our homes.
وانها اصبحت تحدث فارقنا كبيراً.
And so I got myself a job and I was working for a consultancy,
بعد ذلك, حصلت على وظيفة في شركة استشارات،
and we would get in to these meetings,
وكنا نقوم باجتماعات متكررة،
and these managers would come in,
وكان المدراء يأتون إلينا،
and they would say,
قائلين:
"Well, what we're going to do here is really important, you know."
أن ما نقوم بفعله هنا يعتبر في غاية الاهمية.
And they would give the projects code names, you know,
حيث كانوا يقومون بتسمية المشاريع،
mostly from "Star Wars," actually: things like C3PO, Yoda, Luke.
وغالباً كانت هذة الاسماء من حرب النجوم. مثل ( سي ثري بي أو ) , ( يودا ) , ( لووك ).
So, in anticipation, I would be this young designer
في الواقع كنت اصغر المصممين
in the back of the room, and I would raise my hand,
وكنت اجلس في اخر الغرفة وارفع يدي،
and I would ask questions.
واسأل بعض الاسئلة.
I mean, in retrospect, probably stupid questions,
في اعتقادي الان, انها كانت اسئلة سخيفة بعض الشئ،
but things like, "What's this Caps Lock key for?"
مثل ( ماذا يفعل هذا الزر ) ؟؟
or "What's this Num Lock key for?" You know, that thing?
ومافائدة زر قفل لوحة الأرقام ؟؟
"You know, do people really use it?
هل الناس يقمون باستخدامه فعلا ؟؟
Do they need it? Do they want it in their homes?"
هل يحتاجونه ؟؟. هل يهتمون لوجوده بلوحة المفاتيح؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What I realized then is, they didn't really want to change
ما أدركته لاحقاُ, ان الناس يخافون التغيير
the legacy stuff; they didn't want to change the insides.
كالاشياء المتوارثة. فلا يريدون احداث اي تغير.
They were really looking for us, the designers, to create the skins,
في الواقع الناس في حاجة لنا كمصممين . لنحدث التغيير،
to put some pretty stuff outside of the box.
في محاولة للتفكير خارج الصندوق.
And I didn't want to be a colorist.
فلم أشاء ان اكون مصمم تقليدي.
It wasn't what I wanted to do.
لم تكن ما أردت أن أكون.
I didn't want to be a stylist in this way.
لم اكن ارغب في تصميمات عصرية.
And then I saw this quote:
ولاحقا. قرأت هذة المقولة:
"advertising is the price companies pay for being unoriginal."
" الاعلان هو الثمن الذي تدفعة الشركات لتكون غير حقيقية "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, I had to start on my own. So I moved to San Francisco,
فكان يتوجب علي البدء بمفردي . فانتقلت الي " سان فرانسيسكو "
and I started a little company, fuseproject.
وانشأت شركة صغيره تدعى " فيوز بروجكت "
And what I wanted to work on is important stuff.
وماكنت اتطلع اليه. هو العمل على الامور المهمة فعلاً.
And I wanted to really not just work on the skins,
فلم اكن ارغب في صنع ما هو موجود،
but I wanted to work on the entire human experience.
لكن اردت الاستفادة من كل الخبرات السابقة.
And so the first projects were sort of humble,
كان اول اعمالنا متواضع لحد ما،
but they took technology and maybe made it into things
لكننا قما باستخدام التكنلوجيا
that people would use in a new way,
وجعل الناس تستفيد منها بطريقة مبتكرة،
and maybe finding some new functionality.
وذلك بايجاد مشاريع تؤدي مهاما جديدة.
This is a watch we made for Mini Cooper, the car company,
وهذة ساعة صنعناها لشركة سيارات " ميني كوبر "
right when it launched,
في ظهورها الاول في اسواق السيارات،
and it's the first watch that has a display
وكان هذة اول ساعة بشاشة
that switches from horizontal to vertical.
تسمح بعرض الصورة بشكل أفقي وعمودي.
And that allows me to check my timer discretely, here,
فتستطيع مشاهدة الوقت بسهولة،
without bending my elbow.
بدون الحاجة لثني اليد.
And other projects, which were really about transformation,
مشروع اخر .في مجال الابتكار والتغير،
about matching the human need.
لكي يواكب احتياجات الناس.
This is a little piece of furniture for an Italian manufacturer,
هذة قطعة اثاث صغيرة من مصنع ايطالي،
and it ships completely flat,
وهي مسطحة بالكامل،
and then it folds into a coffee table and a stool and whatnot.
وتتحول الى طاولة للقهوه و كرسي.
And something a little bit more experimental:
شي اخر . في طور التجربة:
this is a light fixture for Swarovski,
مصابيح للسقف.
and what it does is, it changes shape.
تتميز بسهولة تغير شكلها.
So, it goes from a circle, to a round, to a square, to a figure eight.
فتتغير من شكل دائري الى مربع و اشكال اخرى،
And just by drawing on a little computer tablet,
وهذا يتم عن طريق الرسم على لوح كمبيوتر،
the entire light fixture adjusts to what shape you want.
فتقوم المصابيح بالتغير الى الشكل الذي تريد.
And then finally, the leaf lamp for Herman Miller.
وهنا ما يدعى بالمصابيح الورقية لـ هرمان ميلر.
This is a pretty involved process;
كانت نتاج عمل جماعي:
it took us about four and a half years.
اخذ منا قرابة الاربع سنوات والنصف.
But I really was looking for creating a unique experience of light,
وما كنا نطمح اليه . هو صنع مصباح فريد من نوعه،
a new experience of light.
تجربة جديده في عالم الاضاءة.
So, we had to design both the light and the light bulb.
فقما بتصميم كل من المصباح و بصيلة الانارة.
And that's a unique opportunity, I would say, in design.
في الواقع هذه الميزة الفريدة في التصميم.
And the new experience I was looking for
والتي كنت اتطلع اليها هي
is giving the choice for the user to go from
اعطاء المستخدم الاختيار ما بين
a warm, sort of glowing kind of mood light,
الاضاءة الهادئة اللماعة،
all the way to a bright work light.
أو الاضاءة الصاخبة.
So, the light bulb actually does that.
وهذا ما تفعلة المصابيح.
It allows the person to switch,
فهي تعطية الحرية لتشغيل،
and to mix these two colorations.
والمزج بين الوان الانارة.
And it's done in a very simple way:
وتتم بصورة بسيطة جداً:
one just touches the base of the light,
فالشخص يقوم فقط بلمس قاعدة المصباح،
and on one side, you can mix the brightness,
في احد الجهات تقوم بضبط مزيج شدة الاضاءة،
and on the other, the coloration of the light.
وفي الجهه الاخرى تقوم بضبط مزج الانارة.
So, all of these projects have a humanistic sense to them,
في الواقع . كل هذة المشاريع ترضى الرغبات بتطورها،
and I think as designers we need to really think
كوني مصمم يحتم علي ان افكر
about how we can create a different relationship
كيف يمكننا صنع علاقات
between our work and the world,
مابين عالمنا الخارجي ومانقوم بعمله،
whether it's for business,
سواء كان لغرض تجاري،
or, as I'm going to show, on some civic-type projects.
او كما ساريكم في بعض المشاريع لاحقاَ.
Because I think everybody agrees that as designers we bring
في الواقع . أظن ان الجميع يتفق بان المصممين يجمعون ما بين
value to business, value to the users also,
قيمة العمل, و فائدته للمستخدم ايضاً،
but I think it's the values that we put into these projects
لكن في اعتقادي بان الاهتمام الذي نمنحه لهذة المشاريع
that ultimately create the greater value.
التي تخلق في نهاية المطاف قيمة أكبر.
And the values we bring
و القيم التي نأتي بها
can be about environmental issues,
يمكن أن تكون حول القضايا البيئية،
about sustainability, about lower power consumption.
حول الاستدامة، اهمية خفض استهلاك الطاقة.
You know, they can be about function and beauty;
فهي على حد سواء للهدف المرجو منها:
they can be about business strategy.
وقد يكون ايضاً لاغراض تجارية اخرى.
But designers are really the glue
لكن المصممين هم حلقة الوصل
that brings these things together.
الذين يقومون بجمع كل هذة الافكار.
So Jawbone is a project that you're familiar with,
" جاو بون " هو مشروع سماعة لا سلكية،
and it has a humanistic technology.
يحتوي على تقنية استشعار.
It feels your skin. It rests on your skin,
تكون هذة السماعة ملامسة للجلد،
and it knows when it is you're talking.
وتميز اذا ما كان الشخص يتحدث.
And by knowing when it is you're talking,
يقوم بتميز كلام الشخص،
it gets rid of the other noises that it knows about,
عن الاصوات الاخرى،
which is the environmental noises.
والضوضاء المحيط بالشخص.
But the other thing that is humanistic about Jawbone
لكن الشئ المميز في " جاو بون "
is that we really decided to take out all the techie stuff,
اننا قررنا ان نستبعد الاجزاء التقنية،
and all the nerdy stuff out of it,
والاشياء المملة،
and try to make it as beautiful as we can.
وحاولنا صياغته بشكل جميل قدر الامكان.
I mean, think about it:
لو فكرنا قليلاً:
the care we take in selecting sunglasses, or jewelry,
فالاهتمام الذي نوليه لشراء نظارة شمسية، او مجوهرات،
or accessories is really important,
او حتى الاكسسوارات, فهو مهم جداً،
so if it isn't beautiful, it really doesn't belong on your face.
لذلك, لو لم يكن منتج جميل فعلاً, فلن يتناسب مع وجه الشخص.
And this is what we're pursuing here.
وهذا ما نريد توضحيه.
But how we work on Jawbone is really unique.
الطريقة التي تعمل عليها لانتاج " جاو بون " تعتبر فريده.
I want to point at something here, on the left.
اود الاشارة الى شئ هنا . على اليسار.
This is the board, this is one of the things that goes inside
هذا لوح للرسم . وهذة احد الاجزاء التي توضع بالداخل
that makes this technology work.
وتسهم في عمل هذة التكنلوجيا.
But this is the design process:
وهنا نرى كيف تتم عملية التصميم:
there's somebody changing the board,
حيث يقوم شخص يقوم بتغير اللوح،
putting tracers on the board, changing the location of the ICs,
ويقوم بعمل بعض التغيرات على اللوح
as the designers on the other side are doing the work.
فيما يقوم المصمم الاخر باكمال العمل.
So, it's not about slapping skins, anymore, on a technology.
فالمراد هنا . ليس الخروج عن طور المالوف بعد الان.
It's really about designing from the inside out.
ولكن التصميم بشكل جديد كليا وغير مسبوق.
And then, on the other side of the room,
ونرى في الناحية الاخرى من الغرفة،
the designers are making small adjustments,
المصممين يقومون ببعض التعديلات،
sketching, drawing by hand, putting it in the computer.
يعدون رسم اولي باليد ثم يدخلونها للكمبيوتر،
And it's what I call being design driven.
وهو ما اسميه الرسم الحر.
You know, there is some push and pull,
بعبارة اخرى هي مجرد محاولات اولية،
but design is really helping define
لكن التصميم عموما يساعد على تحديد
the whole experience from the inside out.
التجربة بوجه كامل.
And then, of course, design is never done.
وحينها يكون التصميم جديد بطريقة استثنائية.
And this is -- the other new way that is unique
وهذة طريقة فرديه من نوعها وجديدة
in how we work is, because it's never done,
نحن نسعى جاهدين لتكون اعمالنا استثنائية مبتكرة،
you have to do all this other stuff.
وبعدها تقوم بتنفيذ باقي المهام.
The packaging, and the website, and you need to continue
كالتغليف والاعلان وباقي المهام
to really touch the user, in many ways.
حتى يحوز المنتج على اعجاب الناس.
But how do you retain somebody, when it's never done?
لكن كيف تتمكن من حفظ براءة الاختراعات من التقليد؟
And Hosain Rahman, the CEO of Aliph Jawbone,
هنا " حُسين رَحمَن " الرئيس التنفيذي لـ" جاو بون "
you know, really understands that you need a different structure.
يقر بان هناك حاجة ماسة لهيكل تنفيذي مختلف.
So, in a way, the different structure is that we're partners,
ويوصف هذة الهيكلة الجديده بانها الشراكة بيننا،
it's a partnership. We can continue to work
في ظل هذة الشراكة تسطيع الاستمرار
and dedicate ourselves to this project,
ونكرس انفسنا لهذة الابداعات،
and then we also share in the rewards.
حتى نصبح شركاء في النجاح.
And here's another project, another partnership-type approach.
وهنا مشروع آخر، نوع اخر من نهج الشراكة.
This is called Y Water,
ويسمى " واي واتر "
and it's this guy from Los Angeles, Thomas Arndt,
هناك شخص من لوس انجلوس يدعى " توماس ارندت "
Austrian originally, who came to us,
من اصل نمساوي، جاء الينا،
and all he wanted to do was to create a healthy drink,
وكل ما كان يطلبة هو انتاج شراب صحي،
or an organic drink for his kids,
او شراب طبيعي صحي للاطفاله،
to replace the high-sugar-content sodas
حتى يكون بديل للعصائر التي تحتوي على الكثير من السكر
that he's trying to get them away from.
والتي كان يحاول جاهدا حتى يبعد اطفاله عنها.
So, we worked on this bottle,
لذلك. قمنا بتصميم هذة القنينة،
and it's completely symmetrical in every dimension.
وهي متشابهة الشكل من جميع الاطراف.
And this allows the bottle to turn into a game.
مما يجل القنينة تبدو كلعبة.
The bottles connect together,
ويمكن جمع اكثر من قنينة،
and you can create different shapes, different forms.
حتى تتمكن من صنع اشكال عديدة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا.
And then while we were doing this,
ثم حين كنا نفعل هذا،
the shape of the bottle upside down reminded us of a Y,
لان شكل القنينة في وضعية مقلوبة يشبة الحرف " Y "
and then we thought, well these words, "why" and "why not,"
وبعدها .. فكرنا بان معناها " لما ولما لا "
are probably the most important words that kids ask.
وهذة هي اكثر الاسئلة التي يطرحها الاطفال عموماً.
So we called it Y Water. And so this is
لذلك قمنا بتسميتها " واي واتر "
another place where it all comes together in the same room:
وفي احدى المرات التي كنا متواجدين فيها جميعا:
the three-dimensional design, the ideas, the branding,
قررنا بان الشكل الثلاثي سيكون الفكرة الرئيسية للمنتج،
it all becomes deeply connected.
ويكون مترابط بشكل تام.
And then the other thing about this project is,
شئ آخر عن هذا المشروع
we bring intellectual property,
عندما استوحينا الفكره،
we bring a marketing approach,
ونهجنا الفكر التسويقي،
we bring all this stuff, but I think, at the end of the day,
وقمنا بكثير من الامور, واخيرا ادركنا،
what we bring is these values,
انا ما نقدمه هو فائدة قيمة للمستهلك،
and these values create a soul for the companies we work with.
وهذة القيمة هي ما تعزز اسم الشركات التي نعمل معها.
And it's especially rewarding when your design work
وما يعتبر نجاحاٌ في حد ذاته هو تصميم عمل
becomes a creative endeavor,
ابداعي , مذهل،
when others can be creative and do more with it.
حيث يستفيد منه الاخرون ايضاً في الابداع.
Here's another project,
وهنا مشروع آخر،
which I think really emulates that.
وهو ما اظن انه يحاكي الابداع.
This is the One Laptop per Child, the $100 laptop.
هذا كمبيوتر محمول للاطفال بقيمة 100$.
This picture is incredible.
هذة الصورة مذهلة فعلاً.
In Nigeria, people carry their most precious belongings on their heads.
في نيجيريا الناس يحملون ممتلكاتهم الثمينة على رؤوسهم.
This girl is going to school with a laptop on her head.
وهذة الفتاة ذاهبة للمدرسة وعلى راسها كمبيوتر محمول.
I mean, to me, it just means so much.
وهذا يعني لي الشئ الكثير.
But when Nicholas Negroponte --
لكن حينا قام " نيكولاس نيقروبونت " --
and he has spoken about this project a lot,
بالتحدث عن هذا المشروع بشكل مفصل،
he's the founder of OLPC -- came to us
بالمناسبه هو مؤوسس " او ال بي سي ". حيث اتى إلينا
about two and a half years ago,
قبل سنتين ونصف تقريباً،
there were some clear ideas.
كان يحمل بعض الافكار الواضحه.
He wanted to bring education and he wanted to bring technology,
كان يطمح الى نشر التعليم باستخدام التكنولوجيا،
and those are pillars of his life,
وكانت هذة مهمتة،
but also pillars of the mission of One Laptop per Child.
ولكن أيضا ركائز لمهمة حاسوب محمول لكل طفل.
But the third pillar that he talked about was design.
المهمة الاخيره. هو تصميم هذا الكمبيوتر.
And at the time, I wasn't really working on computers.
في ذاك الوقت, لم اكن اعمل شخصيا على هذا المشروع.
I didn't really want to, from the previous adventure.
لاني لم ارد خوض المغامرة.
But what he said was really significant,
لكن السؤال الذي يحيره،
is that design was going to be why the kids
كان عن التصميم .. لماذا الاطفال بشكل خاص
were going to love this product,
مالذي سيجذبهم لهذا المنتج.
how we were going to make it low cost, robust.
وكيف يمكننا خفض التكلفة وضمان الجودة،
And plus, he said he was going to get rid of the Caps Lock key --
كما انه اراد الاستغناء عن بعض الازرار كـ " زر الاحرف الكبيرة " --
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
and the Num Lock key, too.
وزر " قفل الارقام " ايضاً.
So, I was convinced. We designed it to be iconic,
لذلك اقتنعت بالفكره. فقمنا بتصميمه ليكون على شكل ايقونات وصور،
to look different. To look like it's for a kid, but not like a toy.
ليبدو مختلفاً, وليبدو كشئ للاطفال, لكن ايضا ليس لعبة.
And then the integration of
وقمنا بجمع
all these great technologies, which you've heard about,
كل التقنيات الجيدة المعروفة،
the Wi-Fi antennas that allow the kids to connect;
مثل اداة الاتصال اللاسلكي, التي تسمح بالاتصال بالانترنت:
the screen, which you can read in sunlight;
والشاشة التي تتميز بسهولة القراءة بوضوح:
the keyboard, which is made out of rubber,
لوحة المفاتيح المصنوعة من المطاط،
and it's protected from the environment.
والبنية القوية التي تحمي المنتج.
You know, all these great technologies really happened
فاستطعنا دمج كل هذة التقنيات
because of the passion and
وكان الدافع هو الرغبه الحقيقه للابداع
the OLPC people and the engineers.
كل من موظفو الشركة ومهندسيها.
They fought the suppliers,
قاوموا الممولين،
they fought the manufacturers.
والمصنعين.
I mean, they fought like animals
بحزم وباصرار
for this to remain they way it is.
حتى يبقون المنتج كما هو.
And in a way, it is that will that makes projects like this one --
وعلى الطريقة التي تجعل المستخدمين يحبون هذا المنتج،
allows the process
والمحافظة على سير العمل
from not destroying the original idea.
حتى يحافظون على الفكرة الاساسية.
And I think this is something really important.
في الواقع اظن ان هذا شئ مهم جداً.
So, now you get these pictures --
اذا, بالنظر الى هذة الصور --
you get up in the morning, and you see the kids in Nigeria
حيث ترون الاطفال في نيجيريا
and you see them in Uruguay
وفي الاوراغواي
with their computers, and in Mongolia.
يحملون كمبيوتراتهم, وفي مانغوليا ايضاً.
And we went away from obviously the beige.
فقد خطونا بعيداً --
I mean it's colorful, it's fun.
فنوعنا في الالوان حتى تصبح مسلية.
In fact, you can see each logo is a little bit different.
حيث ترون بان الشعار يختلف بعض الشئ من جهاز لاخر.
It's because we were able
حيث قمنا
to run, during the manufacturing process,
في طور التصنيع بتثبيت،
20 colors for the X and the O,
عشرون لون لكل من " X و O "
which is the name of the computer,
وهو اسم الكمبيوتر،
and by mixing them on the manufacturing floor,
وبدمجمهم خلال مرحلة التصنيع،
you get 20 times 20: you get
وعند ضرب 20 × 20 تحصل على
400 different options there.
400 خيار من الالوان.
So, the lessons from seeing the kids
والدرس الذي نتعلمه من النظر لهؤلا الاطفال
using them in the developing world are incredible.
وهم يستخدمون هذة الكمبيوترات في تطوير التعليم مذهل.
But this is my nephew, Anthony, in Switzerland,
هذا ابن اخي " انتوني " في سويسرا،
and he had the laptop for an afternoon,
حصل على الكمبيوتر لفترة ما بعد الظهيرة،
and I had to take it back. It was hard.
وحينا اردت استعادته منه, كان ذلك صعبا جداً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it was a prototype. And a month and a half later,
كان مجرد نموذج, وبعد شهر ونصف،
I come back to Switzerland,
عدت الى سويسرا،
and there he is playing with his own version.
وقد وجدته يملك كمبيوتر من صنعه الخاص.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Like paper, paper and cardboard.
من الورق المقوى.
So, I'm going to finish with one last project,
الآن ساختم حديثي بمشورع اخير،
and this is a little bit more of adult play.
وهو نوعاً ما اشبه بلعبة للكبار.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Some of you might have heard about the New York City condom.
قد يكون البعض عنكم سمع عن " واقي نيويورك ".
It's actually just launched, actually launched on Valentine's Day,
قد طرح في الاسواق في عيد الحب مؤخرا،
February 14, about 10 days ago.
في يوم 14 فبراير , اي قبل 10 ايام.
So, the Department of Health in New York came to us,
في البداية اتى الينا المركز الصحي في نيويورك،
and they needed a way to distribute
طالبين المساعدة في توزيع هذا المنتج
36 million condoms for free to the citizens of New York.
وتم توزيع ما يقارب 36 مليون عينة في مدينة نيويورك.
So a pretty big endeavor, and we worked on the dispensers.
كانت فعلا محاولة جيدة, وقمنا بالتركيز على التوزيع الالي:
These are the dispensers. There's this friendly shape.
هذا هو الصيدلي الالي. وهو سهل الاستخدام.
It's a little bit like designing a fire hydrant,
يشبه قليلاً الشكل الاسطواني،
and it has to be easily serviceable:
وهو سهل الاستخدام ومفيد في نفس الوقت:
you have to know where it is and what it does.
عليك معرفة ماهو و ما عمله.
And we also designed the condoms themselves.
وقمنا بتصميم الواقي.
And I was just in New York at the launch,
ولقد كنت في نيويورك في فتره توزيع المنتج للاسواق،
and I went to see all these places where they're installed:
وذهبت لكل المراكز التي تم توزيع المنتج عليها
this is at a Puerto Rican little mom-and-pop store;
هذا متجر " موم اند بوب "
at a bar in Christopher Street; at a pool hall.
وتم توزيعه في نوادي شارع كريستوفر وفي المسابح.
I mean, they're being installed in homeless clinics -- everywhere.
ايضاً تم تزويد العيادات الصحية الحكومية.
Of course, clubs and discos, too.
وفي النوادي ايضاً.
And here's the public service announcement for this project.
وهذا الاعلان الرسمي لها المشروع.
(Music)
(تصفيق)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Get some.
خذ بعض.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, this is really where design
وهنا تتضح امكانية التصميم
is able to create a conversation.
لايصال الفكره.
I was in these venues, and people were,
هذة الاماكن والناس،
you know, really into getting them. They were excited.
التي يذهب اليها الناس باستمرار, مفعمين بالحماس.
It was breaking the ice,
كانت بمثابة كسر للحواجز،
it was getting over a stigma,
لدفع الخجل،
and I think that's also what design can do.
وايضاً امكانية التصميم لايصال الفكره.
So, I was going to
سوف اقوم
throw some condoms in the room and whatnot,
بتوزيع بعض العينات على الحضور،
but I'm not sure it's the etiquette here.
لكني لا اعلم عن قواعد الاتكيت في هذا المكان.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah? All right, all right. I have only a few.
حسناً .. حسناً. لكني املك القليل فقط.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, I have more, you can always ask me for some more later.
لدي المزيد.. ساقوم بتوزيعها في وقت لاحق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And if anybody asks why you're carrying a condom,
واذا قام احد بسؤالكم لما تحملونها معكم،
you can just say you like the design.
يمكنكم القول بان التصميم اعجبكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, I'll finish with just one thought:
حسناً, ساختم بفكرة واحدة:
if we all work together on creating value,
متى ما عملنا جميعنا على تقديم فائدة،
but if we really keep in mind the values of the work that we do,
وركزنا على قيمة العمل الذي نؤديه،
I think we can change the work that we do.
أظن باننا نستطيع تغيير العمل الذي نقوم به.
We can change these values, can change the companies we work with,
نستطيع تغيير القيمة, نستطيع تغيير الشركة التي نعمل بها،
and eventually, together, maybe we can change the world.
اخيراً, اذا اجتمعنا يمكننا تغيير العالم.
So, thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)